A Finding Aid to the Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. artists' letters collection, 1794-1938, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mcgumary
Archives of American Art
Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. artists' letters collection
1794-1938
AAA.mcgumary
Archives of American Art
0.2 Linear feet
The collection of artists' letters compiled by Mary and John McGuigan measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1794-1938. The collection features a group of letters, writings, and signed documents to and from a variety of artists, art administrators, art critics, historians, and art-related organizations. It also includes associated printed material with some documents.
McGuigan, John F, Jr.
McGuigan, Mary K.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated from 2000-2014 by Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan, Jr..
Scope and Contents note
The collection of artists' letters compiled by Mary and John McGuigan measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1794-1938. The collection features a group of letters, writings, and signed documents to and from a variety of artists, art administrators, art critics, historians, and art-related organizations. It also includes associated printed material with some documents.
Letters and signed documents are from William Holbrook Beard, Frederic Edwin Church, Samuel Colman, John Singleton Copley, Kenyon Cox, F.O.C. Darley, Daniel Chester French, Horatio Greenough, Chester Harding, Childe Hassam, Henry Inman, Samuel F. B. Morse, Erastus Dow Palmer, Rubens Peale, Henry Ossawa Tanner, Abbott Handerson Thayer, Stanford White, and Worthington Whittredge, among others.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Series 1: Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. Artists' Letters Collection, 1794-1938 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Biographical/Historical note
Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. are art historians in Milford, Pennsylvania. Together, they purchased artists' letters and associated material at auctions.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Beard, W. H., 1824-1900, (William Holbrook); Church, Frederic Edwin, 1826-1900; Colman, Samuel, 1832-1920; Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1822-1888; French, Daniel Chester, 1850-1931; Greenough, Horatio, 1805-1852; Harding, Chester, 1792-1866 ##naf; Hassam, Childe, 1859-1935; Inman, Henry, 1801-1846; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Palmer, Erastus Dow, 1817-1904; Peale, Rubens, 1784-1865; Tanner, Henry Ossawa, 1859-1937; Thayer, Abbott Handerson; White, Stanford, 1853-1906; Whittredge, Worthington, 1820-1910; Art critics; Artists; Arts administrators; Historians
- Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. Artists' Letters Collection, 1794-1938; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are letters and signed documents are to and from artists, art administrators, art critics, historians, and art-related organizations. Also found are printed materials associated with some documents. Writers include William Holbrook Beard, George Henry Boughton, Joseph Lemuel Chester, Frederic Edwin Church, Joseph Foxcroft Cole, Samuel Colman, John Singleton Copley, Kenyon Cox, F.O.C. Darley, Count Luigi Palma di Cesnola, Gideon Fairman, Kate Fields, Daniel Chester French, Edward Gay, Karl Gerhardt, Horatio Greenough, Chester Harding, Childe Hassam, Henry Inman, John Frederick Kensett, Benson J. Lossing, Clark Mills, Samuel F. B. Morse, Marie Shields Myer, Thoms Nast, John Neagle, James Craig Nicoll, Wallace Nutting, Erastus Dow Palmer, Rubens Peale, Emily Sartain, John Sartain, William Sartain, Robert Sliger, Henry Ossawa Tanner, Abbott Handerson Thayer, Henry T. Tuckerman, Edward Virginius Valentine, Robert W. Weir, Stanford White, and Worthington Whittredge.
  - Beard, William Holbrook, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    William Holbrook Beard, New York, 28 January 1862, to Tallmadge Ewers (1832–1902), Secretary of the Young Men’s Association, Buffalo, regarding that he cannot take less money for his painting Bears on a Bender, but will reduce the price of Grimal Kin’s Dream, both of which are featured in the Buffalo Y.M.A. exhibition that began on 24 December 1861, also mentions two pictures by Worthington Whittredge (1820–1910), and his preparations for a reception in the Studio Building.
  - Boughton, George Henry, 1878-1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    George Henry Boughton, Kensington, London, 12 November 1878, to the engraver Andrew Varick Stout Anthony (1835–1906), regarding an illustration for the 1879 edition of Longfellow’s The Courtship of Miles Standish, which Anthony will engrave, and also mentions Boughton’s new studio and the artists Rossetti and Holman Hunt.
    George Henry Boughton, Maastricht, Holland, 11 October 1881, to the painter and sculptor John Severinus Conway (1852–1925), regarding a tour through Holland and American artists in London including J. A. M. Whistler (1834–1903), Anna Massey Lea Merritt (1844–1930), William Mark Fisher (1841–1923), and William John Hennessey (1839–1917).
    George Henry Boughton, Kensington, London, Thursday [25? April 1889], to the prominent actor Wilson Barrett (1846–1904), regarding a conversation with the art critic Joseph William Comyns Carr (1849–1916) about his and Lawrence Alma-Tadema’s aversion to exhibiting Tadema’s portrait of John Parsons Millet at the Grosvenor Gallery.
  - Chester, Joseph Lemuel, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Joseph Lemuel Chester, prominent genealogist, Washington, DC, 15 May 1858, to Benson J. Lossing (1813–1891), eminent historian and art historian. Regarding Chester's efforts on behalf of house guest Rembrandt Peale (1778–1860) to sell Peale's portrait of Washington, all of which had been facilitated by Lossing.
  - Church, Frederic Edwin, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Frederic Edwin Church, Hudson, 9 February 1892, to Charles Louis Seeger (1860–1943), publisher, exporter, father of poet Alan Seeger and grandfather of folk singer Pete Seeger. Regarding their forthcoming trip together to Mexico, Church's travel arrangements, and their rendezvous in New York City.
  - Cole, Joseph Foxcroft, 1872-1874 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Joseph Foxcroft Cole, Paris, three letters (1872-1874) to Jeremiah Otis Wetherbee (1832–1901), Boston. Wetherbee was a prominent lumber merchant.
  - Colman, Samuel, 1893-1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Samuel Colman, New York, 30 April 1893, to an unknown correspondent, regarding a request for a photograph of the artist, to which he answers that there has never been one on the market.
    Samuel Colman, Greenwich, Connecticut, circa June 1902, to the auctioneer Edward W. Kearney (1852–1918), regarding letter of sympathy about the fatal illness of his wife, Anne Lawrence Dunham Colman (1832–1902), who later died on 28 July in Greenwich.
    Samuel Colman, New York, 30 January 1913, to Dr. Isaac Leopold Rice (1850–1915), regarding a request for correspondence from previous presidents of the National Academy of Design, which he admits he has regretfully destroyed.
  - Copley, John Singleton, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    John Singleton Copley, 29 December 1794, to the collector, engraver, and print-seller Sir John Thane (1748–1818), London, regarding written in the third person, Copley requests portraits of Sir Henry Slingsby, Sir Benjamin Rudyard, Sir Henry Deering, and Francis Rowse for his historical picture of Charles I Demanding in the House of Commons the Five Impeached Members, 1782–1795 (National Portrait Gallery, London).
  - Cox, Kenyon, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Kenyon Cox undated draft fragment of a humorous speech regarding the building of the paintings collection at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.
  - Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Felix Octavius Carr Darley, New York, 24 December 1864, to the publishers Messrs. Ticknor & Fields, Boston, regarding postponing his illustrations for The Vision of Sir Launfal by James Russell Lowell (1819–1891), in order to join the Army of the Potomac for the purpose of making studies for Civil War pictures.
  - di Cesnola, Count Luigi Palma, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Count Luigi Palma di Cesnola, Director of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 25 March 1885, on museum letterhead, to Hayden W. Wheeler (1827–1904), founder of a prestigious jewelry firm in Manhattan. Regarding an invitation to join the Museum board. Includes an engraved portrait of Cesnola.
  - Fairman, Gideon, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Gideon Fairman, Philadelphia, 4 October 1813, to Gorham A. Worth (1783–1856), Cashier of the Farmers and Mechanics Bank, Albany, regarding new bank note designs with small sketch from America’s first prominent engraver.
  - Fields, Kate, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Kate Fields, journalist, prominent literary and arts figure, Washington, DC, 29 April 1892, to John Sartain (1808–1897). Regarding arrangements for Sartain to attend the Art Congress in Washington the following month.
  - French, Daniel Chester, 1899-1931 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    Daniel Chester French, New York, 22 December 1898, to James Large, Philadelphia, regarding a letter of introduction from French, who had been selected by the will of the late Richard Smith (1821–1894) to erect a statue of General George Gordon Meade (1815–1872) for the Smith Memorial Arch in Philadelphia, in order to meet with family members to gain background and images for his work. Envelope addressed to Mrs. John B. Large, Philadelphia and postmarked 11 January 1899. Also included is a letter of introduction from John B. Gest (1824–1907), President of The Fidelity Insurance Trust and Safe Deposit Company, Philadelphia, 22 December 1898, to James Large, on behalf of French.
    Daniel Chester French, New York, 11 January 1899, to Sarah Wise Meade Large, Philadelphia, regarding a visit on Saturday, 14 January 1899, to Philadelphia to secure details for his statue of General George Gordon Meade (1815–1872) for the Smith Memorial Arch in Philadelphia; also hopes to take in the PAFA Exhibition.
    Daniel Chester French, New York, 24 January 1899, to Sarah Wise Meade Large, regarding acknowledgement of receipt of letters and photographs of General Meade, as well as a print by Thomas Hicks, and informs he has begun to sculpt the statue in clay. Also included are two letters to Mrs. Large, one from her mother (undated), and the other from her son’s teacher Robert Anderson of The Episcopal Academy, Lansdowne, Pennsylvania (1911).
    Daniel Chester French, sixty-three typed letters signed on French's own imprinted stationery and two autograph letters signed. New York City, 12 February 1923- 28 March 1931. Written to Charles Dupuy, the caretaker of French's summer home in Massachusetts.
  - Gay, Edward, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Edward Gay, Mt. Vernon, 24 April 1883, to John Elderkin (1841–1926), editor and author. Regarding illustrations for Bayard Taylor's Lars, a previous and forthcoming trip to Norway, and an outstanding commission for Elderkin.
  - Gerhardt, Karl, undated; 1883-1889 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed "Larkin G[oldsmith] Mead." Florence, Italy, 11 June 1883.
    Typed letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed "Abram S. Hewitt." New York, 8 October 1888. On letterhead of Cooper, Hewitt & Co., to Karl Gerhardt, in care of S. L. Clemens, Hartford.
    Autograph note to Mrs. Karl Gerhardt, signed "Mrs. Mackay." Paris, 14 January 1885.
    Typed letter to William Wilson Corcoran, signed by "Franklin P. Gowen." Philadelphia, 29 January, 1885.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "Brander Matthews." New York, 4 January 1886.
    Typed letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "[Senator] Wm. E. Chandler." Washington, DC, 25 June 1888. On United States Senate letterhead.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "[Senator] Jos. R. Hawley." Washington, DC, 10 July 1888. On Senate Chamber letterhead.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "J. R. Hawley." Washington, DC, 8 December 1891.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "Laurence Hutton." Princeton, New Jersey, 21 March 1899.
    Autograph letter to Mrs. Karl Gerhardt, signed by “I. E. Mackay." No location or date given.
    Autograph letter to W. S. Chapman, signed by "Karl Gerhardt." No location or date given.
  - Greenough, Horatio, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Autograph letter signed "Horatio Greenough." Two pages (including integral address leaf). [Washington], not dated. Addressed to Benjamin B. French, Commissioner of Public Buildings in Washington, DC.
  - Harding, Chester, circa 1846-1865 (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
    Chester Harding, Glasgow, Scotland, 21 December 1846, to his son Francis “Frank” Skinner Harding (b. 1843), Springfield, Massachusetts, regarding Harding instructs his youngest son to find Glasgow on the map, pens a sketch of a young boy, and inquires if he has been sledding and obeying his aunts.
    [Chester Harding] Margaret Eliot Harding White (1823–1903), Keene, New Hampshire, to her future sister-in-law Julia Norton Delano, 11 March 1863, regarding White, who edited her father’s memoirs, writes to her future sister-in-law, about to Mary Francis “Frank” Skinner Harding, to congratulate her and learn more about her.
    Chester Harding, Springfield, Massachusetts, 8 September 1863, to his future daughter–in–law Julia Norton Delano, regarding welcoming her to the family.
    [Chester Harding] Mary Ophelia Harding Krum (1818–1892), Chateaugay Lake, New York, 19 July 1864, to her future sister-in-law Julia Norton Delano, regarding summer house with her family and father, Chester Harding, and catching up.
    [Chester Harding] Mary Ophelia Harding Krum (1818–1892), Springfield, Massachusetts, 11 September 1864, to her future sister–in–law Julia Norton Delano, regarding her travels and her return to St. Louis with her father, Chester Harding, as well as warning that her brother Frank’s income, whom she raised, will barely support them after their wedding.
    Chester Harding, Springfield, Massachusetts, 22 December 1864, to his daughter–in–law Julia Norton Delano Harding, Detroit, regarding his wedding gift of money, as well as Frank’s looking into the disposal of his property in Detroit.
    Chester Harding, Springfield, Massachusetts, 15 April 1865, to his daughter-in-law Julia Norton Delano Harding, Detroit, regarding a blunder that cost Frank his job, the poor prospects for Frank’s starting a new business in Detroit, and the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
    Chester Harding, St. Louis, 11 October [1865], to his daughter-in-law Julia Norton Delano Harding, Detroit, regarding the hot weather in St. Louis, his intention to stay until Christmas, and his desire to paint several portraits to keep busy.
    Chester Harding, manuscript fragment, comprising parts No. 2, 3 and 4 of his memoir, A Sketch of Chester Harding, Artist, Drawn by His Own Hand, later edited by his daughter Margaret Eliot Harding White (1823–1903), and published in Cambridge, Massachusetts, by John Wilson in 1866. This is the only known portion of this manuscript.
  - Hassam, Childe, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Childe Hassam, New York, 24 March 1904, to the novelist and playwright Louis Evan Shipman (1869–1933), Cornish, New Hampshire, regarding payment for a painting and an invitation to visit. Includes envelope.
  - Inman, Henry, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Henry Inman, New York, 30 January 1834, to Prosper Montgomery Wetmore (1798–1876), Albany, President of the American Art Union. Regarding his quest to secure the commission to paint one of the panels for the Capitol Rotunda in Washington, DC, as well as a favorable mention of his talent by John Quincy Adams in the New York Mirror. Includes an engraved portrait of Inman.
  - Kensett, John Frederick, circa 1869 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    John Frederick Kensett, Monday, 20 December [ca. 1869], to Richard William Hubbard (1816–88), artist.
  - Lossing, Benson J., 1873 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Benson J. Lossing, eminent historian and art historian, Dover Plains, New York, 2 December 1873, to Morven M. Jones (1815–1886), Utica, New York, attorney, autograph collector, and victim of one of the most scandalous political trials of the Civil War. Regarding the publication of his historical documents.
  - Mills, Clark, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    [Clark Mills] Bank Check for $600 from the National Lincoln Monument Association, Washington, DC, 30 March 1870, paid to “self” and signed by sculptor Clark Mills (1810–1883).
  - Morse, Samuel F. B., 1826 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Autograph letter signed "Sam’l F. B. Morse." Two pages. New York, 30 March 1826. Addressed to Charles R. Leslie, Esq., in London.
  - Myer, Marie Shields, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Marie Shields Myer, 1 June 1912. Invitation from the New York School of Applied Design for Women for an exhibition of Myer's works on view from June through August 1912.
  - Nast, Thomas, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Thomas Nast, Catskill, 29 July 1866, to the Albany architect John B. Halcott (1846–1895), regarding the procurement of current carte de visites of the publisher Thurlow Weed (1797–1892) and former New York Governor Horatio Seymour (1810–1886) for illustrations.
  - Neagle, John, circa 1825-1843 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    John Neagle, ca. 1825–1827, to the theater manager Francis Courtney Wemyss (1797–1859), Philadelphia, regarding Neagle’s busy schedule, his portrait in progress of the actor William Macready (PAFA), that years’ exhibition at the PAFA, his portrait of the actor Junius Brutus Booth (Museum of the City of New York), and that he cannot undertake Wemyss’s portrait anywhere but in his own studio.
    John Neagle, 25 September 1826, to the publisher Matthew Carey (1760–1839), Philadelphia, regarding compiling a list of names and addresses which includes the painter Thomas Sully, the engravers Gideon Fairman, Peter Maverick, James B. Longacre, and Hugh Bridport.
    John Neagle, 24 January 1827, to the publisher Matthew Carey (1760–1839), Philadelphia, regarding the amicable settlement of a dispute through arbitration, and mentions Joseph Hopkinson (1770–1842), President of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and the painter Thomas Sully.
    John Neagle, 26 March 1827, to the publisher Matthew Carey (1760–1839), Philadelphia, regarding Neagle requests the prominent publisher, who has made a solicitation to the artist, what the cost of a church pew will be.
    John Neagle, 9 June 1830, to the publisher Matthew Carey (1760–1839), Philadelphia, regarding Carey’s, a prominent Irish Catholic, “Society for bettering the condition of the Roman Catholics” and Neagle’s desire to become a member.
    John Neagle, 22 July 1843, to Joseph H. Hedges, Philadelphia, regarding acquiring an autograph of Washington Allston, to which Neagle directs him to either of the painters Thomas Sully or Samuel Finley Breese Morse.
  - Nicoll, James Craig, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Letter from J[ames] C[raig] Nicoll to “Mr. Skinner,” 1893 May 29.
  - Nutting, Wallace, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Wallace Nutting clipped letter fragment, June 1938.
  - Palmer, Erastus Dow, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Erastus Dow Palmer, Albany, 18 December 1893, to the sculptor Jonathan Scott Hartley (1845–1912), New York, regarding his affection for his former pupil, the present of a carte de visite of the White Captive, mentions Daniel Chester French (1850–1931), John Quincy Adams Ward (1830–1910), Augustus Saint–Gaudens (1848–1907), and George Inness (1825–94). Includes cdv of the White Captive.
  - Peale, Rubens, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Autograph letter to Honorable M. Dikerson, Secretary of the Navy, signed “Rubens Peale.” New York, 6 June 1837.
  - Sartain, Emily, 1897-1903 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Season ticket to an Exhibition of Works by the Late John Sartain at the Art Club of Philadelphia, 1897. Signed with the compliments of "Emily Sartain."
    Autograph letter to Miss Levy, signed "Emily Sartain." Philadelphia, 28 May 1903. Letterhead: Philadelphia School of Design for Women/ Broad & Masters Streets/ Miss Emily Sartain, Principal
  - Sartain, John, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Autograph letter to Fred. M. Hopkins, signed "John Sartain." Philadelphia, 31 August 1897. Includes sketch for title page of Sartain's book Reminiscences of a Very Old Man.
  - Sartain, William, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Autograph note signed "William Sartain." New York, 7 January 1914.
  - Sliger, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Undated letter envelope from Robert Sliger addressed to himself.
  - Tanner, Henry Ossawa, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Henry Ossawa Tanner, Martigues, France, 11 Febraury 1906, to Mr. Morris.
  - Thayer, Abbott Handerson, circa 1883-1894 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Dictated letter (handwritten) to Sadakichi Hartmann, signed in another hand "A. H.Thayer." Monadnock, New Hampshire, 23 April [no year given].
    Autograph letter to Clara A. May, signed "Abbott H. Thayer." Annotated at top in another hand "21 April 1894."
    Autograph letter to Mr. Koehler, signed "Abbott H. Thayer." Cornwall-on-Hudson, 12 May 1885.
    Autograph letter to Mr. Koehler, signed "Abbott H. Thayer." Cornwall-on-Hudson, 31 October 1883.
    Autograph postcard to Mr. Koehler, signed "A. H. Thayer." Cornwall-on-Hudson, 19 May 1885 [postmark]. Postcard bears letterhead of Magazine of Art-Cassell & Company, Limited.
    Autograph postcard to Mr. Koehler, signed "A. H. T." Postmarked 1886.
  - Tuckerman, Henry T., 1854-1859 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Henry T. Tuckerman, preeminent art critic, New York, 6 November 1854, to Benson J. Lossing (1813–1891), eminent historian and art historian. Regarding Tuckerman's desire to obtain a copy of Lossing's profusely illustrated Pictorial Field Book of the Revolution (1851) and inquiring about his progress on Pictorial Field Book of the War of 1812 (1862).
    Henry T. Tuckerman, New York, 4 June 1859, to Benson J. Lossing (1813–1891). Regarding Tuckerman's refusal of an editorship, Lossing's Field Book, and a dispute with Mr. Putnam over the authorship of a Peale painting.
  - Valentine, Edward Virginius, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Edward Virginius Valentine, Richmond, 12 March 1877, to Dr. James M. Minor, New York, regarding Minor’s returning his bust of General Robert E. Lee to him in Richmond.
  - Weir, Robert W., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Robert Walter Weir, Green’s Farms, Connecticut, 12 July 1884, to Mr. Campbell, regarding life at his summer residence, and an inquiry regarding Hannah White (1748–1841) of Plymouth, whose portrait Weir had painted when she was in her 80’s, and who as a girl had known Elder Faunce, one of the early settlers of the colony.
  - White, Stanford, 1892-1895 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Typed letter signed "White" on the imprinted stationery of McKim, Mead & White. Two separate pages, four total. New York, 16 November 1895. To Frederick William MacMonnies.
    Typed letter signed "Stanford White" with holograph additions and three-line holograph postscript, on the imprinted stationery of McKim, Mead & White. Two separate pages, four total. New York, 19 January 1892. To Frederick William MacMonnies.
    Typed letter signed "Stanford White" with holograph sketch, on the imprinted stationery of McKim, Mead & White. Two pages, Quarto. New York, 25 February 1892. Written to Frederick William MacMonnies.
  - Whittredge, Worthington, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Worthington Whittredge, New York, 2 February 1879, to Andrew Varick Stout Anthony (1835–1906), American wood engraver.